Finding Aid for Michigan Central Railroad Company records, 1837-1928
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Michigan Central Railroad Company records 1837-1928
Michigan Central Railroad Company.
87354 Bb 2
Letter books, 1883-1921, of company president and general manager (outgoing only); administrative records, including contracts, financial papers, and miscellanea; manuscript and printed agreements between MCR and other railway lines; volumes of letters received, 1846 and 1860 (fragmentary); time books, 1853-1872, detailing hours and wages on the Detroit-Chicago section of the railroad; and miscellaneous scattered correspondence of Alpheus Felch, James F. Joy, and William Woodbridge.
25.3 linear feet in 26 boxes
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
These records have come from different sources (primarily donor nos. 7310, 6480, 1856, 8027, and 6901 ). The largest portion of the collection came from Syracuse University Library (donor no. 4454 ) in 1991.
The record group is open to research.
On March 20, 1837, legislation providing for work to proceed on three railroads and two canals in Michigan became law. One of the railroads -- the central -- was to connect Detroit and St. Joseph through the second tier of counties. Based upon preliminary work already done by the Detroit and St. Joseph Railroad Company (whose rights and properties were purchased by the state), the railroad was able to begin operation (at least as far as Dearborn) by the end of 1837. In 1846, the central railroad was sold by the state to a group of investors that included John W. Brooks of Massachusetts and Detroit attorney James F. Joy who incorporated the railroad as the Michigan Central Railroad Company. By this time the central railroad extended as far as Kalamazoo. One of the terms of the sale was that the railroad would reach Lake Michigan within three years. In 1852 the line was extended to Chicago. Over the next half century, the Michigan Central would lease or otherwise gain control of smaller railroad lines serving other parts of the state. In 1930, the Company would be itself leased into the New York Central Railroad system. In 1976 and 1978, properties of MCR were conveyed to Consolidated Railroad and Penn Central Railroad respectively.
The Michigan Central Railroad Company record group is an amalgam of various records received from different donors. The materials have been divided into the following series: James F. Joy Administrative Records and Agreements; Letters Received; Miscellaneous; President/General Manager/Chairman files; and List of Stockholders.
Subjects:
Business records.; Railroads--Michigan--Employees.; Michigan Central Railroad Company.
Contributors:
Felch, Alpheus, 1804-1896.; Joy, James F. (James Frederick), 1810-1896.; Woodbridge, William, 1780-1861.
- James F. Joy Administrative Records and Agreements
  The James F. Joy Administrative Records and Agreements series came from the AMTRAK Depot in Detroit in the Spring of 1986. These were largely the papers of attorney James Frederick Joy (1810-1896), generated in the fifty years of his association with the Michigan Central Railroad. In 1846 Joy framed the company charter and acted as legal counsel for the corporation which purchased it from the state. As a specialist in railway litigation, Joy was largely involved in the extension of the Michigan Central's lines. In 1867 he became company president.
  - Administrative Records
    The Administrative Records subseries includes contracts (for real estate and with suppliers of railroad materials, such as steel); financial papers such as bank drafts, freight bills, invoices and records of bank accounts; and maps of proposed new territory for the expanding Michigan Central Railroad. Also included here are such miscellaneous documents as a proposal to build the Chicago and Michigan Lakeshore Railroad, and records of money toward its construction. Finally, this series contains J.F. Joy's correspondence, largely concerning the railroad business between 1851 and 1876.
    - Contracts
      - Land (Box 1)
      - Other, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Correspondence 1851-1876, undated (Box 1)
      (include correspondence of Alpheus Felch and William Woodbridge)
    - Financial records (Box 1)
    - Maps (Box 1)
      (maps have been separately cataloged and located in library's map collection)
    - Miscellaneous, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Agreements
    The Agreements subseries includes both manuscript and printed records of agreements between the Michigan Central Railroad and other railway lines.
    - Manuscript A-F, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Manuscript G-Z, 4 folders (Box 2)
- Letters Received
  The Letters Received series (received from donor nos. 6480 and 8027) is a fragments of what must have been a much larger set of records. These are but five volumes from what must be at least over 150 volumes. The volumes date from before 1847 to October 1860 with many gaps.
  - Volume 1, prior to January 1, 1847 (Box 2)
  - Volume 58 February 1853 (Box 2)
  - Volume 79 November 1854 (Box 2)
  - Volume 112 February 1860 (Box 2)
  - Volume 150 October 1860 (Box 2)
- Miscellaneous
  The Miscellaneous series includes time books, 1853-1872, recording names of laborers, and hours and wages on the Detroit-Chicago section of the railroad; two scrapbooks containing photographs and article clippings of locomotives and rolling stock, and miscellaneous accounts and receipts.
  - Time books (Detroit-Chicago section)
    (donor no. 1856)
    - 1853-1872 (Box 2)
  - Notice of first meeting August 1846 (Box 2)
    (donor no. 6901)
  - Receipts, miscellaneous accounts, etc. 1846-1847 (Box 2)
  - Scrapbooks
    - Locomotives 1853-1927 (Box 2)
    - Rolling Stock 1870-1928 (Box 2)
  - Agreements (printed), 8 volumes (Box 3)
    (include four volumes with duplicate copies)
- President/General Manager/Chairman
  In 1991, the library received from Syracuse University Library the largest series in the collection: Letter books of the president, general manager and chairman, 1883-1921. These 187 volumes consist of outgoing responses only and detail the administrative and financial operations of the railroad. This accession also includes letter books of outgoing telegrams, 1883-1921, and letter books relating to the Detroit Railway Tunnel and the building of the new station in Detroit, 1911-1915.
  - Letter books
    - January 23, 1883-October 13, 1884, 13 volumes (Box 4)
    - October 13, 1884-April 12, 1886, 13 volumes (Box 5)
    - April 13, 1886-April 4, 1888, 13 volumes (Box 6)
    - April 4, 1888-April 5, 1890, 13 volumes (Box 7)
      (missing volume no. 43, September-November 1888)
    - April 5, 1890-December 28, 1891, 12 volumes (Box 8)
      (missing volume no. 65, October-November 1891
    - December 28, 1891-January 19, 1893, 9 volumes (Box 9)
      (missing volume nos. 76-78, January-May 1893)
    - May 12, 1893-September 3, 1894, 9 volumes (Box 10)
      (missing volume nos. 86-87, February-May 1894)
    - September 3, 1894-February 4, 1896, 11 volumes (Box 11)
    - February 4, 1896-March 27, 1897, 10 volumes (Box 12)
    - March 27, 1897-June 15, 1898, 11 volumes (Box 13)
    - May 30, 1898-July 28, 1899, 11 volumes (Box 14)
    - July 28, 1899-July 12, 1900, 9 volumes (Box 15)
    - July 12, 1900-July 5, 1901, 9 volumes (Box 16)
    - July 5, 1901-June 16, 1902, 9 volumes (Box 17)
    - June 16, 1902-May 28, 1903, 8 volumes (Box 18)
    - May 28, 1903-July 28, 1904, 8 volumes (Box 19)
    - July 28, 1904-May 7, 1907, 8 volumes (Box 20)
    - May 7, 1907-September 23, 1914, 5 volumes (Box 21)
      (missing volume nos. 186, January 1909-June 1910 and 188-189, January 1912-May 1913)
    - September 23, 1914-May 12, 1921, 6 volumes (Box 22)
      (missing volume no. 197, May 1918-May 1919)
  - Telegrams
    - June 29, 1883-December 23, 1891, 12 volumes (Box 23)
      (missing volume no. 1)
    - December 24, 1891-November 17, 1902, 11 volumes (Box 24)
    - November 17, 1902-May 2, 1921, 4 volumes (Box 25)
  - Detroit Railway Tunnel letter book August 26, 1904-December 24, 1918, 2 volumes (Box 25)
  - New Station letter book May 2, 1911-July 4, 1915, 2 volumes (Box 25)
  - Reduction of expenses letter book June 12, 1911-December 5, 1911, 1 volumes (Box 25)
- Lists of stockholders
  The Lists of stockholders series is a surviving fragment of three volumes covering three years within the period of 1878 to 1885.
  - 1878, 1881, 1885, 3 volumes (Box 26)